Alvin G. Thomas Curriculum vitae

CONTACT Information

Johns Hopkins University E-mail: alvin@jhmi.edu
School of Medicine, Department of Surgery Github: alvinthomas
2000 E. Monument St. Twitter: @alvinthomas13
Baltimore, MD 21205 USA LinkedIn: @alvinthomas13

# RESEARCH INTERESTS

Utilizing Epidemiologic Methods in Transplantion: My research explores clinically imporant epidemiologic questions at the intersections of solid organ transplantation, aging, infectious disease, and health policy. I am also involved in the development of a number of eHealth tools designed to connect, educate, and empower transplant donors and recipients.

# CURRENT POSITION

Research Data Analyst, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Department of Surgery Epidemiology Research Group in Transplantation August 2016 to present

#### EDUCATION

# Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD

MSPH, International Health, May 2016

- Focus: Global Disease Epidemiology and Control (GDEC)
- Thesis: The mLAKE Community Trial: Using mHealth to Empower CHWs to Encourage Combination HIV Prevention
- Adviser: Larry W. Chang, MD, MPH

#### Washington and Lee University, Lexington, VA

BS, Chemistry-Engineering, May 2014

- Honors in Engineering
- Minor in Poverty and Human Capabilities
- Thesis: Plasticity in Dissociated Neuronal Networks under Chronic Stimulation
- Adviser: Jonathan Erickson, PhD

# PEER-REVIEWED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- [1] **Thomas AG**, Henderson ML, Shaffer A, Massie AB, Luo X, Holscher CM, Purnell TS, Lentine K, Segev DL. The National Landscape of Living Kidney Donor Follow-up in the United States. *American Journal of Transplantation*. In Press. doi:10.1111/ajt.14356
- [2] Long A, Mbabali I, Hutton HE, Thomas AG, Bugos E, Mulamba J, Amico KR, Nalugoda F, Gray RH, Wawer MJ, Nakigozi G, Chang LW. Design and Implementation of a Community Health Worker HIV Treatment and Prevention Intervention in an HIV Hotspot Fishing Community in Rakai, Uganda. Journal of the International Association of Providers of AIDS Care. In Press. doi:10.1177/2325957417709089
- [3] Perin J, **Thomas AG**, Oldja L, Ahmed S, Parvin T, Bhuyian SI, Sarker B, Biswas SK, Faruque AS, Sack RB, and George CM. Geophagy is associated with growth faltering in children in rural Bangladesh. *The Journal of Pediatrics*. 2016 Nov 30; 178:34-9. doi:10.1016/j.jpeds.2016.06.077

# SUBMITTED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

 Ruck JM, Zhou S, Thomas AG, Cramm SL, Massie AB, Montgomery JR, Berger JC, Henderson ML, Segev DL. Electronic messaging and communication with living kidney donors. Submitted 2017.

- [2] McAdams-DeMarco MA, Ying H, Thomas AG, Warsame F, Shaffer AA, Haugen CE, Garonzik Wang JM, Desai NM, Varadhan R, Walston J, Norman SP, Segev DL. Frailty, Inflammation, and Mortality Among Patients with End-Stage Renal Disease. Submitted 2017.
- [3] Durand CM, Bowring MG, Kucirka LM, Thomas AG, Massie AB, Bohm MK, Cameron A, Desai NM, Sulkowski M, Segev DL. The Impact of the Drug Overdose Epidemic on Deceased Donation and Transplantation in the United States. Submitted 2017.
- [4] Haugen CE, Thomas AG, Garonzik Wang J, Massie AB, Segev DL. Minimizing Risk Associated with Older Liver Donors by Matching to Preferred Recipients: A National Validation Study. Submitted 2017.
- [5] Van Pilsum Rasmussen SE, Thomas AG, Garonzik Wang J, Henderson ML, Stith SS, Segev DL, Nicholas LH. Reported Effects of the SRTR 5-tier Rating System on US Transplant Centers. Submitted 2017.
- [6] Shaffer AA, Thomas AG, Bowring MG, Van Pilsum Rasmussen SE, Kucirka L, Alqahtani S, Gurakar A, Sulkowski M, Cameron A, Segev DL, Durand CM. Changes in Practice and Perception of Hepatitis C and Liver Transplantation: Results of a National Survey. Submitted 2017.
- [7] Henderson ML, DiBrito SR, **Thomas AG**, Holscher CM, Shaffer AA, Bowring MG, Purnell TS, Massie AB, Garonzik-Wang JM, Waldram M, Lentine KL, Segev DL. Brief Communication: Living Multi-organ Donors in the United States. Submitted 2017.
- [8] Kumar K, Tonascia JM, Muzaale AD, Purnell TS, Ottmann SE, Al Ammary F, Bowring MG, Poon A, King EA, Massie AB, Chow EKH, Thomas AG, Ying H, Borja M, Konel JM, Henderon ML, Cameron AM, Garonzik-Wang JM, Segev DL. Racial differences in completion of the living kidney donor evaluation process. Submitted 2017.

### Conference Talks

[1] <u>Henderson ML</u>, **Thomas AG**, Massie A, Luo X, Shaffer A, Holscher C, Segev DL. The Unfunded OPTN/UNOS Mandate of Living Kidney Donor Follow-up: Fewer than 50% of Centers in Compliance. In: *American Transplant Congress*, Chicago, IL, USA, April 29 - May 3, 2017.

# Conference Posters

- [1] **Thomas AG**, Shaffer A, Massie A, Segev DL. Use of Pulsatile Perfusion Modifies the Effect of Delayed Graft Function on Graft Failure. In: *American Transplant Congress*, Chicago, IL, USA, April 29 May 3, 2017.
- [2] <u>Thomas AG</u>, Massie A, Garonzik-Wang J, Lentine K, Henderson M, Segev DL. Landscape of Multiple Donations from a Living Donor in the US. In: *American Transplant Congress*, Chicago, IL, USA, April 29 - May 3, 2017.
- [3] Shrestha P, Rasmussen S, **Thomas AG**, Ferguson S, Massie A, Segev DL. Access to Living Donor Kidney Transplantation in Nepal. In: *American Transplant Congress*, Chicago, IL, USA, April 29 May 3, 2017.
- [4] Halpern SE, Thomas AG, Holscher C, Massie A, Henderson ML, Anjum S, Locke J, Segev DL. Sexual Dysfunction Among Living Kidney Donors. In: American Transplant Congress, Chicago, IL, USA, April 29 May 3, 2017.
- [5] <u>Bannon J</u>, Wickliffe C, **Thomas AG**, Klingbell A, Hiller J, Halpern S, Segev DL, Henderson ML. An Interdisciplinary Task Force to Engage Living Kidney Donors and Improve Follow-up Compliance. In: *UNOS Transplant Management Forum*, Orlando, FL, USA, April 25-27, 2017.

- [6] Thomas AG, Henderson ML, Massie AB, Shaffer A, Luo X, Holscher CM, Segev DL. Fewer than 50% of Transplant Centers Fully Comply with OPTN Living Donor Follow-up Policy. In: American Society of Transplant Surgeons, Miami, FL, USA, January 26-29, 2017.
- [7] <u>Hapern SE</u>, **Thomas AG**, Holscher CM, Massie AB, Henderson ML, Anjum S, Locke JE, Segev DL. Sexual Dysfunction Among Living Kidney Donors. In: *American Society of Transplant Surgeons*, Miami, FL, USA, January 26-29, 2017.
- [8] Long A, Hutton H, Mbabali I, Thomas AG, Bugos E, Mulamba J, Amico KR, Nalugoda F, Gray R, Wawer M, Nakigozi G, Chang LW. Evaluation of a Motivational Interviewing-Informed, mHealth-Supported CHW Training Program to Promote HIV Treatment and Prevention in a HIV Hotspot Ugandan Fishing Community. In: International Association of Providers of AIDS Care, Fort Lauderdale, FL, USA, May 9-11, 2016.
- [9] Chang LW, Mbabali I, Kong X, Hutton H, Long A, Thomas AG, Bugos E, Ssekasanvu J, Kennedy C, Amico KR, Nalugoda F, Reynolds SJ, Quinn T, Serwadda D, Gray R, Wawer M, Nakigozi G. A Cluster-Randomized Trial to Promote Combination HIV Prevention Using mHealth-Supported CHWs in a High-Prevalence Ugandan Fishing Community: Design and Baseline Characteristics of the mLAKE Trial. In: International AIDS Conference, Durban, South Africa, July 18-22, 2016.
- [10] Thomas AG, Erickson J, Strickland K, Barnes A. Iterative Gaussian mixture model splitting of multimodal PSTH for studying activity dependent changes in cultured network connectivity. In: Society for Neuroscience, San Deigo, CA, USA, November 9-13, 2013.
- Presentor(s) underlined

#### INVITED TALKS

[1] The National Landscape of Living Kidney Donor Follow-up in the United States. In: American Society of Transplantation and American Journal of Transplantation Journal Club, Online, December 7, 2017.

# TEACHING EXPERIENCE

# Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD

Guest Lecturer May 2017

- 340.600.01: Stata Programming
  - Graduate course in intermediate Stata programming
  - Main instructors: Dorry L. Segev, Allan B. Massie
  - Lecture: "Lab: From a Dirty Dataset to Table 1"
  - Enrollment: 281

### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

#### Research Data Analyst | Johns Hopkins University | 2016-Present

 Responsible for data analysis and manuscript preparation for >20 research projects in transplantation epidemiology. Manage data for an ongoing NIH-funded prospective study of living donors. Support the development of novel eHealth technologies for kidney donors engagement. Develop and maintain statistical software in R and Stata. Advisor: Dorry Segev, MD PhD

## Research Assistant | Rakai Health Science Program | 2015-2016

• Trained community health workers and study staff involved in the implementation of two NIH-funded studies in Rakai, Uganda. Developed the standard operating procedures for data quality and management and contributed to the development of study questionnaires and protocols. Developed analytic R scripts to regularly generate weekly study implementation reports. Assisted in the development and testing of two mHealth applications. Advisor: Larry Chang, MD MPH.

# Data Manager | Johns Hopkins University | 2016

 Performed data management activities to ensure data quality using SAS, EpiInfo, and Stata for the NSEBA Study which aims to improve detection of pediatric HIV in Zambia. Advisor: Catherine Sutcliffe, PhD.

#### Research Assistant | International Vaccine Access Center | 2014-2015

• Abstracted data from >100 journal articles for a systematic review that aimed to estimate the global burden of Haemophilus influenza type B, Streptococcus Pneumoniae, and Neisseria meningitides.

### Student Reseracher | Shepherd Poverty Program | 2013

• Analyzed data from the CDC Health, 2011 report to present longitudinal data analysis on the relationship between socioeconomic status and health status. Funded by the University Research Scholarship. Advisor: Harlan Beckley, PhD

# Biomedical Engineering Technician | Engineering World Health | 2013

• Fully repaired 20 medical devices, took full inventories of the Rubavu hospital and its ten surrounding health clinics, and conceptualized a novel medical device to perform lab equipment calibrations in resource-scarce environments.

# AMERICORPS SERVICE

#### Robotics Program Founder | Lexington City Schools | 2011-2014

 Created and ran a program that uses Lego NXT robots to introduce middle school and elementary students to robotics, computer science, and engineering design utilizing a \$2500 grant from NSF.

# Shift Leader | Campus Kitchens Project | 2011-2014

• Addressed local hunger as a ServSafe-certified manager by supervising shifts that collected, prepared, and served over 300 meals/week.

#### Trip Coordinator | Volunteer Venture Program | 2011-2013

• Coordinated three weeklong service trips for incoming students, which involves budget management and logistical planning.

#### Therapeutic Nursery Intern | Kennedy Krieger Institute | 2011

• Conducted play-therapy sessions with homeless toddlers and their families. Provided care for the children and assisted with an active study in child psychology.

### Patient Eligibility Intern | Rockbridge Area Health Center | 2010-2012

• Helped manage the medical database, helped eligible patients acquire free medication from pharmaceutical companies, and answered patient questions by phone.

# SOFTWARE SKILLS

## Statistical/Numerical Analysis:

• Stata, R, SAS, MATLAB, Maple

#### Computer Programming:

• Java, C++, C, Python, SQL

#### Version Control:

• Git (GitHub/GitLab)

#### Productivity and Editing Software:

- Atom, Xcode, RStudio
- TeX (LATeX, BibTeX)
- $\bullet\,$  Microsoft Office, Libre Office, Google Docs, iWork, End<br/>Note
- GIMP, Adobe Photoshop

#### Operating Systems:

• Apple MacOS, Microsoft Windows, Linux (Fedora, SGE)

#### Awards

#### American Transplant Congress 2017

- Best of Congress Poster for "Use of Pulsatile Perfusion Modifies the Effect of Delayed Graft Function on Graft Failure"
- Poster of Distiction for "Use of Pulsatile Perfusion Modifies the Effect of Delayed Graft Function on Graft Failure"

## Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health

• Center for Global Health Established Field Placement/Pilot Grant, 2015

#### Washington and Lee University

- Algernon Sydney Sullivan Award, 2014
- Omicron Delta Kappa Leader of the Year, 2014
- Sigma Pi Sigma Physics Honor Society, 2013
- Johnson Opportunity Grant, 2013
- Evans International Grant, 2013
- Avis P. Waring Scholarship, 2013
- Omicron Delta Kappa Leadership Honor Society, 2013
- Beta Beta Beta Biological Honor Society, 2011
- Bonner Scholarship, 2010
- Johnson Scholarship, 2010-2014